So the question is, what is invisible?
اذا السؤال هو، ما هو غير المرئي؟
There is more of it than you think, actually.
في الحقيقة ،هنالك أكثر مما تتوقعون.
Everything, I would say. Everything that matters
كل شيء، بل أقول، كل الأشياء المهمة.
except every thing and except matter.
عدا كل شيء، وعدا المادة.
We can see matter. But we can't see what's the matter.
نستطيع رؤية المادة. لكننا لا نستطيع أن نرى ما هو الأمر.
As in this cryptic sentence I found in The Guardian recently:
كما في هذه الجملة المبهمة التي وجدتها في الجارديان مؤخرا.
"The marriage suffered a setback in 1965,
"الزواج عانى عقبة في 1965
when the husband was killed by the wife."
عندما قتلت الزوجة زوجها"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
There's a world of invisibility there, isn't there?
هنالك عالم من الإبهام، أليس كذلك؟
So, we can see the stars and the planets,
اذن نستطيع أن نرى النجوم والكواكب.
but we can't see what holds them apart
لكننا لا نستطيع رؤية ما يبقيهم بعيدين عن بعضهم،
or what draws them together.
أو ما يقربهم من بعضهم.
With matter, as with people, we see only the skin of things.
بالمادّة، كما بالناس، نرى فقط قشرة الاشياء.
We can't see into the engine room.
لا نستطيع أن نرى ما في داخل غرفة المحرّك.
We can't see what makes people tick, at least not without difficulty.
لا نستطيع رؤية ما يحرك الناس، علي الأقل بسهولة.
And the closer we look at anything, the more it disappears.
و كلما نظرنا لأي شيء عن قرب، كلما اختفى أكثر.
In fact, if you look really closely at stuff,
في الواقع، اذا نظرت عن قرب أكثر للأشياء،
if you look at the basic substructure of matter,
اذا نظرت الى جوهر الأشياء الأساسي ،
there isn't anything there.
فلا شيء هناك .
Electrons disappear in a kind of fuzz,
الألكترونات تختفي في غموض،
and there is only energy. And you can't see energy.
وتبقي فقط الطاقة، ولا نستطيع رؤية الطاقة.
So everything that matters, that's important, is invisible.
اذا كل الأشياء المهمة خفية.
One slightly silly thing that's invisible
شيء واحد خفي به بعض السخف
is this story, which is invisible to you.
هو هذه القصة، وهي خفية بالنسبة لك.
And I'm now going to make it visible to you in your minds.
وسوف أجعلها مرئية لكم داخل عقولكم.
It's about an M.P. called Geoffrey Dickens.
إنها عن عضو في البرلمان يدعي جيفري ديكنز.
The late Geoffrey Dickens, M.P. was attending a fete in his constituency.
الراحل جيفري ديكنز،عضو البرلمان، كان يحضر أحد المناسبات في دائرته الإنتخابية.
Wherever he went, at every stall he stopped he was closely followed
وكلما ذهب لأحد العارضين كان متبوعا عن قرب
by a devoted smiling woman of indescribable ugliness.
بإمرأة مبتسمة قبيحة لدرجة لا يمكن وصفها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Try as he might, he couldn't get away from her.
حاول قدر المستطاع لكنه لم يستطع الابتعاد عنها.
A few days later he received a letter from a constituent
بعد عدة أيام تلقي خطابا من ناخبة
saying how much she admired him,
تقول أنها معجبة به,
had met him at a fete and asking for a signed photograph.
وأنها قابلته في أحد المناسبات وتطلب صورة موقعة منه.
After her name, written in brackets was the apt description, horse face.
بعد إسمها كتبت بين أقواس الوصف الملائم، وجه الحصان.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"I've misjudged this women," thought Mr. Dickens.
"لقد أسات الحكم علي هذه المرأة"، أعتقد السيد. ديكنز.
"Not only is she aware of her physical repulsiveness,
"أنها ليست فقط مدركة لشكلها المنفر،
she turns it to her advantage.
بل أنها تحوله لميزة.
A photo is not enough."
الصورة لا تكفي."
So he went out and bought a plastic frame to put the photograph in.
فخرج وإشتري إطار بلاستيك للصورة.
And on the photograph, he wrote with a flourish,
وعلي الصورة كتب بشكل واضح,
"To Horse Face, with love from Geoffrey Dickens, M.P."
"إلي وجه الحصان، مع حبي من جيفري ديكنز عضو البرلمان"
After it had been sent off, his secretary said to him,
وبعد إرسالها، قال له سكرتيره،
"Did you get that letter from the woman at the fete?
"هل تلقيت هذا الخطاب من تلك المرأة التي رأيتها في الحفل؟
I wrote Horse Face on her, so you'd remember who she was."
لقد كتبت عليها وجه الحصان حتي تتذكر من هي"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I bet he thought he wished he was invisible, don't you?
أراهن أنه تمني ان يكون غير مرئي، ألا تعتقدون؟
So, one of the interesting things about invisibility
إذن، أحد الخواص الشيقة لكون الأشياء مخفية
is that things that we can't see
هو ان الأشياء التي لا نستطيع رؤيتها
we also can't understand.
هي أيضا غير مفهومة لنا.
Gravity is one thing that we can't see
الجاذبية هي أحد الأشياء التي لا نستطيع رؤيتها،
and which we don't understand.
ولا نفهمها.
It's the least understood of all the four fundamental forces,
إنها أقل الأشياء المفهومة في القوي الأساسية الأربعة،
and the weakest.
وأضعفها.
And nobody really knows what it is or why it's there.
ولا يعرف أحد ماهيتها ولا لما هي موجودة.
For what it's worth, Sir Isaac Newton, the greatest scientist who ever lived,
أغلب الظن، سير إسحق نيوتن، أعظم العلماء علي مر العصور،
he thought Jesus came to Earth specifically to operate the levers of gravity.
أعتقد أن المسيح أتي إلي الأرض خصيصا لتحريك قوي الجاذبية.
That's what he thought he was there for.
هذا في رأيه سبب وجود المسيح.
So, bright guy, could be wrong on that one, I don't know.
إذن رجل ذكي من الممكن أن يكون علي خطأ في هذا، لا أعرف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Consciousness. I see all your faces.
الوعي . أنا أري كل وجوهوكم.
I have no idea what any of you are thinking. Isn't that amazing?
ليس لدي أدني فكرة عما تفكرون فية، أليس ذلك مذهلاً؟
Isn't that incredible that we can't read each other's minds?
أليس مذهلا أننا لا نستطيع قراءة أفكار بعضنا البعض.
But we can touch each other, taste each other perhaps, if we get close enough.
لكننا نستطيع لمس بعضنا البعض، حتي تذوق بعضنا، لو أقتربنا بما فيه الكفاية.
But we can't read each other's minds. I find that quite astonishing.
لكننا لا نستطيع قراءة أفكار بعضنا البعض. أجد ذلك مذهلاً.
In the Sufi faith, this great Middle Eastern religion,
العقيدة الصوفية، الديانة الشرق أوسيطة العظيمة،
which some claim is the route of all religions,
التي يزعم البعض أنها الطريق لكل الأديان،
Sufi masters are all telepaths, so they say.
مشايخ الصوفية يتخاطبون عن طريق توارد الأفكار، هكذا يقولون.
But their main exercise of telepathy
لكن أهم ممارساتهم لتوارد الأفكار
is to send out powerful signals to the rest of us that it doesn't exist.
هو إرسال إشارات قوية لنا أن هذا غير موجود.
So that's why we don't think it exists,
ولهذا نعتقد أنه غير موجود.
the Sufi masters working on us.
المعلمون الصوفيين يؤثرون علينا.
In the question of consciousness
في مسألة الوعي
and artificial intelligence,
والذكاء الإصطناعي.
artificial intelligence has really, like the study of consciousness,
الذكاء الأصطناعي حقيقة، كدراسة الوعي،
gotten nowhere. We have no idea how consciousness works.
لم يصل لنتيجة. ليس لدينا أدني فكرة عن كيف يعمل الوعي.
With artificial intelligence, not only have they not created artificial intelligence,
في حالة الذكاء الإصطناعي، لم يستطيعوا خلق ذكاء إصطناعي,
they haven't yet created artificial stupidity.
ولا حتي غباء إصطناعي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The laws of physics: invisible, eternal, omnipresent, all-powerful.
قوانين الفيزياء : غير مرئية ، أبدية ، منتشرة في كل مكان ، وكلها قوية.
Remind you of anyone?
ألا تذكرك بأحد؟
Interesting. I'm, as you can guess,
أنا ، كما يمكنك تخمين ،
not a materialist, I'm an immaterialist.
لست مادياً، علي العكس.
And I've found a very useful new word, ignostic. Okay?
ولقد وجدت كلمة جديدة مفيدة جدا "لا نستطيع التأكد من وجود الله" . حسنا؟
I'm an ignostic.
أنا لا أؤمن بإمكانية التأكد من وجود الله.
I refuse to be drawn on the question of whether God exists,
وأرفض أن أدخل في مسألة هل الله موجود أم لا.
until somebody properly defines the terms.
حتي يستطيع أحد أن يعرف بدقة المصطلحات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Another thing we can't see is the human genome.
شيء أخر لا نستطيع رؤيته هو الجينوم البشري.
And this is increasingly peculiar,
وهذا أمر غريب على نحو متزايد.
because about 20 years ago, when they started delving into the genome,
لأن منذ حوالي 20 عاما مضت ، عندما بدأوا الخوض في الجينوم ،
they thought it would probably contain around 100,000 genes.
ظنوا أنه يحتوي على الأرجح علي حوالي 100 ألف من الجينات.
Geneticists will know this, but every year since,
علماء الجينات سوف يعرفون هذا ، ولكن في كل عام منذ ذلك الحين ،
it's been revised downwards.
يتم خفض هذا الرقم.
We now think there are likely to be only just over 20,000
ونعتقد الآن أن من المحتمل أن تكون هناك ما يزيد قليلا عن 20 ألف.
genes in the human genome.
من الجينات في الجينوم البشري.
This is extraordinary. Because rice -- get this --
هذا خارق للعادة. لأن الأرز ، ركزوا معي،
rice is known to have 38 thousand genes.
الأرز من المعروف أنه يحتوي علي 38 ألف جين.
Potatoes, potatoes have 48 chromosomes. Do you know that?
البطاطس ،البطاطس تحتوي علي 48 من الكروموسومات. هل تعرف ذلك؟
Two more than people,
اثنين أكثر من الناس.
and the same as a gorilla.
وبالمثل الغوريلا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You can't see these things, but they are very strange.
لا يمكنك مشاهدة هذه الأشياء. لكنها غريبة جدا.
The stars by day. I always think that's fascinating.
النجوم بمرورالأيام. دائما ما أعتقدت أن هذا رائع.
The universe disappears.
الكون يختفي.
The more light there is, the less you can see.
كلما زاد الضوء، كلما قلت قدرتك علي الرؤية.
Time, nobody can see time.
الوقت ، لا أحد يستطيع أن يرى الوقت.
I don't know if you know this. Modern physics,
أنا لا أعرف إذا كنت تعرف هذا. الفيزياء الحديثة ،
there is a big movement in modern physics
هناك حركة كبيرة في الفيزياء الحديثة
to decide that time doesn't really exist,
لتقرير إذا كان الوقت لا وجود له في الواقع.
because it's too inconvenient for the figures.
لأنه غير ملائم للأرقام.
It's much easier if it's not really there.
انه من الاسهل بكثير اذا لم يكن هناك فعلا.
You can't see the future, obviously.
لا يمكنك رؤية المستقبل ، ذلك واضح.
And you can't see the past, except in your memory.
ولا تستطيع رؤية الماضي ، إلا في ذاكرتك.
One of the interesting things about the past is
واحدة من الأشياء المثيرة للاهتمام عن الماضي هو
you particularly can't see. My son asked me this the other day,
أنك تحديداً لا تستطيع رؤيته، إبني طلب مني هذا في أحد الأيام،
he said, "Dad, can you remember what I was like when I was two?"
وقال : "أبي هل نتذكر كيف كنت عندما كنت في الثانية؟"
And I said, "Yes." And he said, "Why can't I?"
وقلت "نعم". وقال : "لماذا لا استطيع أنا؟"
Isn't that extraordinary? You cannot remember
أليس هذا مذهلا؟ لا يمكنك التذكر
what happened to you earlier than the age of two or three,
ما حدث لك في وقت ما قبل سن الثانية أو الثالثة.
which is great news for psychoanalysts,
وهو شيء رائع بالنسبة للمحللين النفسيين.
because otherwise they'd be out of a job.
وإلا سيصبحون بلا عمل.
Because that's where all the stuff happens
لأن هذا هو وقت حدوث كل الاشياء
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
that makes you who you are.
هذا ما يشكلك.
Another thing you can't see is the grid on which we hang.
شيء آخر لا يمكنك رؤيته هو الشبكة ، الذي نتعلق بها.
This is fascinating. You probably know, some of you,
هذه رائع. ربما كنتم تعرفون ، البعض منكم ،
that cells are continually renewed. You can see it in skin and this kind of stuff.
الخلايا تتجدد باستمرار. يمكنك أن ترى ذلك في الجلد وما إلي ذلك.
Skin flakes off, hairs grow, nails, that kind of stuff.
الجلد يتقشر،الشعر ينمو ، الأظافر ، وهذا النوع من الاشياء.
But every cell in your body is replaced at some point.
ولكن كل خلية في جسمكم يتم استبدالها في مرحلة ما.
Taste buds, every 10 days or so.
خلايا التذوق، حوالي كل عشرة أيام.
Livers and internal organs sort of take a bit longer. A spine takes several years.
الكبد والأعضاء الداخلية تأخذ فترة أطول قليل نوعا ما. والعمود الفقري يستغرق عدة سنوات.
But at the end of seven years, not one cell in your body
ولكن بمرورسبع سنوات ، ولا خلية واحدة في جسمك
remains from what was there seven years ago.
ستبقي كما كانت قبل سبع سنوات.
The question is, who, then, are we?
والسؤال هو ،إذن من نحن؟
What are we? What is this thing that we hang on,
ما نحن؟ ما هو الشيء الذي نتعلق به ،
that is actually us?
الذي هو في الواقع نحن؟
Okay. Atoms, you can't see them.
حسنا. الذرات ، لا يمكنكم رؤيتها.
Nobody ever will. They're smaller than the wavelength of light.
لا أحد سيستطيع. انهم أصغر من طول موجة الضوء.
Gas, you can't see that.
الغاز ، لا يمكنك رؤية ذلك.
Interesting. Somebody mentioned 1600 recently.
من المثير للاهتمام. شخص ما ذكر 1600 في الآونة الأخيرة.
Gas was invented in 1600
تم اخترع الغاز في عام 1600
by a Dutch chemist called Van Helmont.
بواسطة كيميائي هولندي يدعي فان هيلمونت.
It's said to be the most successful ever invention
ويقال أنه أنجح اختراع علي الإطلاق
of a word by a known individual.
لكلمة بواسطة شخص معروف.
Quite good. He also invented a word called "blas,"
حسناُ. قد اخترع كلمة "blass" أيضا،
meaning astral radiation.
وتعنى إشعاع نجمي.
Didn't catch on, unfortunately.
ولم تعلق بالأذهان للاسف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But well done, him.
لكن قد أحسن عملاُ.
There is so many things that -- Light.
هناك الكثير من الامور التي -- الضوء.
You can't see light. When it's dark, in a vacuum,
لا يمكنك رؤية الضوء. في الظلام ، في فراغ ،
if a person shines a beam of light straight across your eyes,
إذا سلط أحد الأشخاص شعاع من الضوء مباشرة عبر عينيك ،
you won't see it. Slightly technical, some physicists will disagree with this.
لن ترى ذلك. علمياً، بعض علماء الفيزياء سوف نختلف مع هذا.
But it's odd that you can't see the beam of light,
ولكن من الغريب أنك لن يمكنك رؤية شعاع الضوء ،
you can only see what it hits.
يمكنك ان ترى فقط ما يسقط عليه.
I find that extraordinary, not to be able to see light,
أجد ذلك غير عادي ، عدم القدرة على رؤية الضوء ،
not to be able to see darkness.
عدم القدرة على رؤية الظلام.
Electricity, you can't see that.
الكهرباء ، لا يمكنك رؤيتها.
Don't let anyone tell you they understand electricity.
لا تسمح لأحد أن يقول لك أنهم يفهمون الكهرباء.
They don't. Nobody knows what it is.
أنهم لا يفهمونها. لا أحد يعرف ماهيتها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You probably think the electrons in an electric wire
ربما كنتم تفكرون أن الإلكترونات في سلك الكهرباء
move instantaneously down a wire, don't you, at the speed of light
تتحرك على الفور عبر سلك ، ألا تعتقد ، في سرعة الضوء
when you turn the light on. They don't.
عند تشغيل الضوء. لا يفعلوا ذلك.
Electrons bumble down the wire,
الالكترونات تتعثر عبر السلك ،
about the speed of spreading honey, they say.
في سرعة انتشار العسل ، كما يقولون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Galaxies, 100 billion of them estimated in the universe.
المجرات ، 100 مليار منها ، تقدر في الكون.
100 billion. How many can we see? Five.
100 مليار. كم منها يمكن أن نرى ؟ خمسة.
Five out of the 100 billion galaxies, with the naked eye,
خمسة من أصل 100 مليار مجرة ، بالعين المجردة.
and one of them is quite difficult to see unless you've got very good eyesight.
واحدة منهم من الصعب جدا أن تراها ما لم يكن لديك بصر جيد جدا.
Radio waves. There's another thing.
موجات الراديو. هذه شيء آخر.
Heinrich Hertz, when he discovered radio waves in 1887,
هاينريش هيرتز، عندما اكتشف موجات الراديو عام 1887 ،
he called them radio waves because they radiated.
سماها موجات الراديو لأنها تشع.
And somebody said to him,
وقال أحدهم له،
"Well what's the point of these, Heinrich?
"حسنا ما هي الفائدة من هذا هاينريش؟
What's the point of these radio waves that you've found?"
ما الفائدة من الموجات الراديو التي إكتشفتها؟ "
And he said, "Well, I've no idea.
وقال : "حسنا ، ليس لدي فكرة.
But I guess somebody will find a use for them someday."
ولكن اعتقد شخص ما سيجد استخدام لها يوما ما ".
And that's what they do, radio. That's what they discovered.
وهذا ما فعلوه ، الراديو. هذا ما اكتشفوه.
Anyway, so the biggest thing
على أي حال ، أهم شيء
that's invisible to us is what we don't know.
غير مرئي بالنسبة لنا هو ما لا نعرفه.
It is incredible how little we know.
ومن المذهل قلة ما نعرف.
Thomas Edison once said,
توماس اديسون قال ذات مرة ،
"We don't know one percent of one millionth
"اننا لا نعرف واحد في المئة من واحد في المليون
about anything."
عن أي شيء ".
And I've come to the conclusion --
ولقد وصلت إلى استنتاج
because you've asked this other question, "What's another thing you can't see?"
لأنكم قد سألتم هذا السؤال الآخر , "ما هو الشيء الأخر الذي لا تستطيع أن تراه؟"
The point, most of us. What's the point?
الهدف، معظمنا، ما هو الهدف؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
You can't see a point. It's by definition dimensionless,
لا يمكنك أن تري الهدف. انه ، بحكم تعريفه ، بلا أبعاد ،
like an electron, oddly enough.
للغرابة مثل الألكترون.
But the point, what I've got it down to,
لكن الهدف, ما وصلت إليه
is there are only two questions really worth asking.
أنه هناك سؤالان فقط حقا يستحقان أن نسألهم.
"Why are we here?" and "What should we do about it while we are?
"لماذا نحن هنا؟" و "ما الذي يجب علينا القيام به بينما نحن موجودون؟
And to help you, I've got two things to leave you with, from two great philosophers,
ولمساعدتكم ،عندي شيئين سأتركهم لكم ، من اثنين من الفلاسفة العظام،
perhaps two of the greatest philosopher thinkers of the 20th century,
ربما اثنين من أعظم الفلاسفة المفكرين في القرن العشرين.
one a mathematician and an engineer, and the other a poet.
واحد عالم رياضيات ومهندس ، والأخر شاعر.
The first is Ludwig Wittgenstein who said,
الأول هو لودفيج فيتجنشتين الذي قال,
"I don't know why we are here.
"أنا لا أعرف لماذا نحن هنا.
But I'm pretty sure it's not in order to enjoy ourselves."
ولكن انا متأكد جداُ من انه ليس من أجل التمتع. "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He was a cheerful bastard wasn't he?
لقد كان وغدا مرحاُ أليس كذلك؟
And secondly and lastly, W.H. Auden,
وثانيهما وأخيرهما، دبليو .إتش. أودن،
one of my favorite poets, who said,
واحد من شعرائي المفضلين، قال:
"We are here on earth
"نحن هنا على الأرض
to help others.
لمساعدة الآخرين.
What the others are here for, I've no idea."
لمَ الآخرون هنا, ليس لدي فكرة"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)